[Music]
welcome to the sense-making series so a
few days ago a friend of mine asked me
what I thought was going on and I told
him that the pandemic was kind of like
an altered state and it had just acted
as a catalyst for a lot of things that
were already there like the psychologist
Stan Grof describes psychedelics as
effectively nonspecific amplifiers they
just magnify what's already there so I
think what's happened with the pandemic
is that it's acted as a catalyst for all
of the things that are under the surface
all of the fault lines and the problem
of truth is right at the center the
collapse of institutional Authority the
lack of a replacement and how we make
sense of the world together and lots of
the things that rebel wisdom has been
talking about for the last couple of
years in particular the sense-making
crisis how do we know what's true how
can we discuss what's true what can be
talked about what can't be talked about
and how can we have conversations that
move us into fresh territory so with
sense making it's all of these questions
of how is information weaponized on all
sides what are the psychological issues
what are the ideological issues so we're
going to unpack all of that over the
next few weeks and I've said before it
feels like we're in some interregnum
period between two worlds the trust in
the old system broadcast media academia
and all these other ways of finding
truth is collapsing under the onslaught
mostly of decentralized networked media
but we don't have a networked solution
to the problem of truth and this feels
like a really really dangerous place to
be we've lost one structure and we're in
this kind of no-man's land between
before we get to another stable
structure and central to this has to be
social media the influence of big tech
but also what is done to us as people
where communication starts being
performative where everything is
happening in public I'm going to play a
short clip from Jonathan Hite now from
the Sam Harris podcast so I began to
feel around 2014-2015 that something was
deeply wrong like like something has
changed about the universe suppose that
suppose that God one day
I just doubled the gravitational
constant so you know in our universe
there's like 25 physical constants and
if God just said one day let's just
double the gravitational constant just
for fun like everything would go totally
haywire in the physical world and you
know planets would move in their orbits
and planes would come out of the sky and
it would just be you know bizarre and
disastrous and I think that what
happened is basically that but in the
social world it's the nature of the
connectivity its connectivity in which
we are communicating not privately but
in front of an audience and the audience
rates the communication so this I think
is what social media has done to us on
the subject of the big tech platforms
later in the series we're going to hear
from Tristan Harris sometimes called the
conscience of Silicon Valley and Carl
Miller of the Center for the analysis of
social media when you kind of sit down
and you talk to people that have
actually done in from influence
operations in information warfare and
the first thing that you learn from them
is that they barely ever try to convince
you of something that you didn't already
think was true about the world it's much
much much easier to influence you and
change your behavior on the basis of
giving you from information which
already confirms what you think is true
about the world make you even anger
about the things that you think are true
about the world and then direct what
you're gonna do about with all that
anger into one direction or another and
and they will tell you there is
absolutely no and point really liked
people most of the time because you can
build an extremely distorted picture the
world simply through the judicious
selection of some facts over another so
I'm gonna start this series by going
back to some things that we've covered
in the past on rebel wisdom because the
issues that that brought up are now even
more pressing than they were before
in particular the intellectual dark web
phenomenon so we did quite a lot of
pieces around the intellectual dark web
concept at around the time of the first
big rebel wisdom piece glitch in the
matrix so I'm gonna play another quick
clip introducing what the intellectual
dark web is the
- that tall dark web was first named by
the mathematician and physicist Eric
Weinstein on Sam Harris's waking up
podcast in January 2018 it attempted to
join together an unlikely group of
intellectuals and alternative media
personalities all the way from
psychologist Jordan Peterson to
podcaster and martial arts commentator
Joe Rogan figures from across the
political spectrum but all supposedly
united by their willingness to have open
and difficult conversations the name
stuck interest in the phenomenon quickly
spread far and wide with many thousands
joining the conversation online welcomed
by some ridiculed by others and even
questioned by some in the group it's
like a herd of cats right because so
I've thought about well what what what
unites us to the degree that there's an
us because that's not so self-evident
there's enough of enough so that the
name emerged and it's stuck
so so there's something in common
because otherwise the name wouldn't have
stuck right you can't name nothing it
doesn't work so what is the intellectual
darkweb people in the group tend to
reject orthodoxy tend to reject ideology
tend to be interested in first
principles thinking meaning that if you
you don't take something on faith you
need a group of people who are willing
to say hey you know you made a better
point I changed my mind and I've learned
something that I didn't think about and
that kind of integrity in a conversation
is what characterizes a lot of the
internal IDW discussion to me it's that
people agree not on their positions they
may not even agree as to what the facts
are but they usually agree as to what
constitutes conversation
so the reason for focusing on this is
because I think the problem that it was
responding to is the key problem how do
you have conversations across
ideological lines how do you talk about
things where there's a real social cost
to talking about it I'm going to have
some criticisms of the intellectual diet
web as it was constellated and as it
played out in a way I think the
intellectual dart web died as soon as it
was named in a paradox as soon as it
appeared in The New York Times with
Barry Weiss's article it was no longer
dark and it was very easily attacked as
saying well how can you say that this is
the dark web when Joe Rogan has 7
million subscribers Sam Harris is one of
the biggest podcasters in the world and
there's some truth obviously to that
critique so I think something like it
has to be recovered we have to have some
way of having these conversations and
widen it out maybe beyond where the
intellectual dark web was first
constellated so it's very difficult to
talk about these things without going
into politics for what it's worth I
think the left-right division is less
useful than it's ever been my personal
background I would describe myself as a
disaffected liberal I was brought up in
a very left-wing family and like many
people I feel politically homeless
because the left now is not what the
left used to be when I was growing up
but I also see how that particular
observation can also be weaponized as
well and be used for political ends the
main criticism of the IDW at the time
was that it was right-wing and
reactionary which is clearly not true
when you have left wingers like sam
Harris Eric and Brett Weinstein within
it but there is some truth that it was
constellated around an opposition to the
excesses of social justice culture or
that it was anti identity politics and I
think that that was true it was to
Constellation around a position that was
saying that identity politics has gone
too far
and one of the more sophisticated
arguments against the IDW was that it
was blowing a small problem out of
proportion it was just confined to
university campuses it wasn't that big
wasn't a big problem but now in 2020
there's been a huge sea change just in
the last few days in particular a lot of
journalists who were previously on the
other side of the argument starting to
say that something very significant
happening in journalism there's been a
very famous blow-up in the New York
Times which has led to the opinion
editor having to leave the paper and
this recent article by Matt Taibbi says
that there's been revolt in at least
eight different newsrooms around the
u.s. now I've got friends who are still
in newsrooms in the UK and they say the
same thing has basically been happening
here it's been summarized particularly
in these tweets by Barry Weiss who was
the person who wrote the original IDW
article as effectively a revolt by new
woke journalists against older liberal
journalists the older liberal
journalists staying more - a kind of
freedom of speech position and the new
generation having more of a kind of
harm's focus saying that certain types
of speech of violence certain types of
speech should not be given place in the
paper all of these arguments which
directly go against the old tradition of
open debate and free speech so much has
changed that even Matt Iglesias one of
the original founders of the ultra woke
Vox posted this tweet saying he would
have to apologize for saying that it was
confined to just university campuses as
Brett Weinstein the evolutionary
biologist and one of the original
members of the IDW said in one of our
films this is not just consigned to
university campuses so we are all
watching something move across the
landscape and alter what can be said
where it can be said at what kinds of
language have to be used and many people
will tell you nobody really believes
that and then others will tell you oh
it's a tiny number of people so it's
you're blowing the danger out of
proportion but those of us who are
paying attention to it are watching the
institution after institution be
lobotomised by these arguments that
really don't rise to the level of a good
discussion in a college dorm these are
not high quality arguments they are not
robust in the face of what is understood
as a result of decades or in some cases
centuries of study and different
disciplines so how is it that these
wrong arguments carry so much power
that's the question the answer in
general is that game
theory provides loopholes where people
can have power that is disproportionate
to their numbers and disproportionate to
the power of the logic underlying what
they are saying
so the wielding of stigma in such a way
that causes people to be much more
likely to voice one perspective than the
counter perspective understanding the
the biases that exist as a result of a
sometimes cynical use of game theory so
I think it's time to review the IDW to
go back through history look at what
they got right look at what they got
wrong and then think about what might
come next how can we find a way of
arriving at truth together so tomorrow
I'm gonna post a talk that I gave at a
university last year called my journey
with the IDW I almost called it the IDW
is dead but change my mind at the last
minute and then shortly after that I'm
going to post some interviews that I've
done quite recently with Eric and Brett
Weinstein and then later in the
sense-making series I'm going to talk to
experts on information warfare the
nature of the big tech platforms and
other perspectives on the problem of
truth and I'm also going to talk to
critics of members of the intellectual
dark web as well so right now I'm gonna
play some clips from some older rebel
wisdom films all on the topic of sense
making some from people who are in the
IDW some from people who weren't
starting with Eric Weinstein who coined
the term as I came to understand that we
were in some sort of society-wide Ponzi
scheme since the late 60s early 70s and
that there was no way to continue to
grow our way out
using the previous tools I started to
understand that society was going to be
lying about almost everything at almost
all times and that's a very terrifying
thought to have we have effectively
entered a period in which we cannot
trust our experts and I think that what
began as a desire to contribute it to do
real work ended with an understanding
that we've got two generations of
institutional experts that are corrupted
and that we cannot wake up from this
crazy fever dream that we're all in
because we can't figure out who we can
still trust the doctors are compromised
that professors are compromised the
journalists are compromised the
politicians are compromised about the
only thing that isn't badly compromised
are people with an independent source of
sustenance individuals and very small
groups are about the only thing that is
free of this disease of the embedded
growth obligation and so the paradox is
is that the individuals have to save the
institutions that are trying to
extinguish them because the
institution's don't want to hear this
message but in fact if they don't make
use of the tiny number of people
functioning as individuals or in small
organizations all of this is going to
collapse I think what we need is we need
to realize that the diversity of ideas
that have to be explored hinges are not
allowing in bad diversity that is you
don't want a single person at the table
who wants to scuttle the conversation
and that's not something that we've
understood about the modern left the
modern left is very often focused on
scuttling any realistic conversation so
that it can continue to threaten and
terrorize people into pretending to hold
positions that no sane person could
possibly hold why do you think it's
become like this well I think my wife
probably has the best explanation which
is that when you're actually dependent
on labor for your voter base labour has
economic issues so this is the great
search for something cheaper than labor
and identity turns out to be much
cheaper than labor if you can get
somebody to vote for you
where you're gonna take their future
their security and their retirement but
you're going to celebrate the fact you
know that they came from Laos that's a
bad deal nothing against the Laotians
but for God's sake stand up for yourself
as a worker before you you know stand up
for yourself as somebody who needs to
see Southeast Asia celebrated on the
national stage
it's not that exciting demand more from
from your representatives this is the
great search for the cheapest possible
constituency and that's exactly why I
think it's happening I think it's
because the traditional Democratic voter
base was too expensive they wanted real
change they wanted to participate
economically they wanted to participate
at the level of power and the donor base
said is there isn't there anything
cheaper than labour and I think they
found something I'm gonna link to all of
these films in the show notes below so
Bret Weinstein and his wife Heather hi
Inge were famously involved in the
Evergreen uprising and had to leave the
College in 2017 really worth watching
Mike Nana's films looking at what
happened then what's really interesting
about Heather and Bret's situation given
that Evergreen was definitely one of the
most progressive colleges in the country
is that they were teaching evolutionary
biology the reality of sex differences
some of the topics that are hardest to
talk about at the moment in progressive
circles and they were talking about them
for a decade before the uprising
happened and they were forced to leave
Evergreen so I wanted to know how they
managed that and what lessons they had
for talking about some of these very
difficult topics the thing that the IDW
has done is it has bootstrapped that
kind of safety on topics where people
experience in general a profound lack of
safety so I think the reason that there
has been such a focus on the IDW is that
people through the internet can watch
others saying things the very nuance of
which would cause them to blow up if you
said them you know in a speech on a
university campus let's say and watching
people have those discussions and
respond to each other in spite of
disagreement and not have catastrophe
rein in on them is I think heartening in
fact I know that that's the reaction
because I hear a lot from individuals
who tell me what they see and they are
cheering for the the simple
demonstration that these conversations
are still possible and if you were to
distill down what say three or four
principles of having a generative
conversation in good faith ah what would
they be what conditions allow for that
so how do you know you're having one
maybe like what are what are the what
are the signals that you're actually
doing it right but you're actually
having a good conversation
no wrote apologies apologies for actual
wrongs but no wrote apologies do not
apologize for things that you did not
actually do and if you see sort of a
culture of rote apology in a big
conversation
there's probably fear right underneath
the surface similarly I would say look
for laughter look for humor look look
for and not just you know there's
everyone can tell the difference between
a nervous laughter and and regular from
the gut laughter in which things even
when you didn't see something coming or
maybe that's often when things get funny
when a conversation that was very
serious or very technical suddenly
erupts and laughter if that can happen
there's probably not fear right beneath
the surface and and obviously laughter
is also a way that people people bond as
I'll explain a bit more in my talk
tomorrow there was always a bit of
unclarity with the intellectual dark web
something that Eric Weinstein who came
up with the term will say was deliberate
was it a set of people was it a set of
good faith principles this was never
entirely made clear so a lot of people
were linked to it a lot of people were
officially in it according to the the
article in The New York Times one of my
favorite ideas comes from a developer
called Ryan Bennett who came up with
what he called the IDW protocol in a set
of tweets and his point was we don't
understand the internet by looking at
the contents of people's hard drives he
fundamentally misunderstood the nature
of the internet if you try and do that
the internet is a set of protocols it's
a set of ways of
interacting that create something bigger
than itself what if we could come up
with a crowd-sourced set of principles
that would equate to kind of good-faith
dialogue if so this is something that
Heather and Brett also talked about
having a covenant in their class to be
able to talk about these subjects and
what do you think of the principles for
discussing these kind of topics that you
could take from your experience at
Evergreen and take out into the world
certainly having some sort of a document
in advance that everyone has agreed to
is incredibly useful you also need
someone who's willing to and enabled to
enforce it and in the modern
authoritarian left landscape enforcers
are always seen as bad you know
hierarchy is a societal patriarchy and
all of this the problem is you will
immediately not having such a covenant
you will immediately trip over the
following problem if you attempt it the
Covenant is exclusionary what you are
really saying when you set out an
agreement about how we will talk and
disagree and challenge each other is you
are saying that if you don't agree to
these rules you're not welcome here
now nobody likes to hear you're not
welcome here and at the moment that sets
people off it's I have a hair-trigger
for being told somebody's not welcome
there who are you to say who's welcome
at a point as well no I'm not telling
you you're not welcome I'm telling you
anyone who doesn't agree to this set of
good faith principles isn't welcome and
as soon as you do agree then you are so
you're the one deciding whether you're
welcome or not having decided to live by
these rules then you get the benefits of
what is in effect a much more capable
but more fragile conversation and this
is I think one of the hardest lessons of
well the hardest lessons for me at least
of complex systems is that very often
the most capable creatures or mechanisms
are also the ones with the narrowest
requirements so that a beautifully
architected creature may have very
precise limits on what a cantar
the beautiful conversation that is
capable of traversing some new landscape
and doing it deftly that conversation
does not happen when anybody can law any
accusation at any moment with no
evidence it happens when people are
protected enough to try out difficult
things and then to adjust their position
and learn where they've arrived and
before we move on to some of the other
sense-making frameworks that I think are
really important one thing I would
really say is that from the beginning
the intellectual darkweb for me and for
many other people was missing a
developmental lens and this was a really
important piece developmental psychology
how we grow how we develop and even
though Jordan Peterson was a big fan of
Jean Piaget who was a developmental
psychologist the intellectual dark web
didn't have that component to it and the
most famous exponent of that is probably
Ken Wilber an integral theory and I
spoke to him and he laid out some really
really useful frameworks for
understanding what's going on Ken Wilber
is the creator of integral theory
another attempt to pull together much of
the world's knowledge and spiritual
traditions into a theory of everything
integral theory gained a big following
in the 90s and 2000's and remains
influential after serious health
problems over the last decade Ken Wilber
is now returning to the conversation at
the core of integral theory is the idea
that cultures and societies go through
specific levels of development in the
same way as individuals do becoming more
sophisticated as they develop or grow up
it's an idea that's common to
developmental theorists including
Peterson's favorite Jean Piaget you move
from one knowledge structure to the next
one which includes the previous one and
is better and it's better because it
covers more territory that's how you
know it's better it does the same thing
the old tool does plus some additional
things so it's a definition of better
integral theory represents this
development as a spiral in this film
will mostly be talking about
Amba tribalism ethnocentric
authoritarian which first emerged about
five
thousand years ago orange modern values
the rational self that emerged 300 years
ago with the liberal democracies and the
beginning of universal values green the
values of relativism multiple
perspectives dialogue and consensus
human rights sometimes called postmodern
which emerged fully in the 1960s if
they're healthfully integrated they
support each other but each of them can
believe that their way of looking at the
world is the only true way and then they
are mutually exclusive for Wilbur the
incomprehension between these worldviews
is what's causing many of the worst
excesses of the culture wars above these
levels Wilbur says is another level
called integral or second-tier from this
perspective it's clear that each of the
previous ways of seeing the world has
value and needs to be integrated as we
started to get this both polarization
and and that included regression in many
cases you just these absolutist ik re
tribal eyes points of view where people
again if they were discussing their
tribe they weren't saying this is what
my tribe has in common with this tribe
and this tribe in this services this is
how my tribes different from that tribe
you need to serve some sort of special
something or other and again there very
well could be tribes that deserve
special attention certainly but the
point is if you're just emphasizing that
and you're not emphasizing how that
tribe is part of a unified overall
tribal structure then that is just retry
belies a ssin that is regression and the
only ultimate end point of that really
is just warfare and an is just no way
around it and humanity fought 300
thousand years to get over that stage so
among other things it could bring in
women's rights and bring in
an end a slavery and bring in the end of
the intouchables
and start including every minority you
can think of LGBTQ transgender this was
extraordinary but as I started to fall
apart and get rocking went started to
get left out as green became just
extreme absolutist ik and started
devolve attorney ilysm and narcissism or
even request to absolutist ethnocentric
the only people you had supporting these
original liberal values which are
absolutely crucial to any higher stage
the whole point about these stage is the
development is that each higher stage
again transcends but includes the
previous stage and grand and
transcendence include orange transcended
and repressed orange that's definition
of pathology that's when the real
problems with that so if you have an
integral thinker and they're looking out
there to see what is really missing is
that's what that's how and it's real
think who thinks is wait there's a
little bit of truth in all of this
however we including all of these things
and you're thinking that way and you
look out there and and if you are for
example a professor teaching at a
university one of the things you start
to notice is this extraordinary lack of
traditional liberal values after we
covered the IDW rebel wisdom continue to
look at the topic of sense making and to
seek out people who had really
interesting and useful frameworks to
make sense of things one of those who I
think is really essential to understand
is Jordan Hall and his concept of
decentralized versus broadcast media and
the concept of the blue church and game
a I want to play a short clip from that
here
[Music]
the blue church emerged in the context
of having to figure out how to navigate
all of these changes in generate
coherence how do we get all of these
people with these new capacities to be
able to make sense of the world in some
fashion that is able to then make
choices together and to act effectively
right that's the question and the blue
church developed to be the answer to
that question answer develop the ability
to say for example use the education
system to establish an embodied sense of
vertical meritocratic hierarchy the idea
that some people are better at others in
knowing certain kinds of things we can
find them and then we empower them to
have hierarchical Authority in the
structure that we're in and I should say
this by the way both formally and
informally you know the role of being in
class is teaching that whether the
content of the story of the of the Klatt
whatever the content of class is the
experience of the student is the
teachers in charge our job is just to
listen and some of us are smart and they
get to be teachers or in charge right
that's kind of that's the story of
school and it's very important that
first part that there's a relationship
between authority and receptor that has
a broadcast modality so the blue church
is very broadcast across its entire mode
so what I mean by broadcast of course is
exemplified in television which is to
say that some small number of people get
to speak and a very very large number of
people get to listen
[Music]
we talked about discernment and how
that's a key skill in decentralized
media compared to broadcast media oh
absolutely so so now the the
conversation which i think is really
nice is turning to now what and how so
the answer now what is decentralized
active intelligence great how how do we
do that
so I said first step is know that you
don't know know that most of your habits
are blue church habits in fact most your
average even gamej habits but let's just
leave it up to the church right now and
certainly everything you've been
formally taught and everything you've
learned from formal institutions and
almost all those are gonna be wrong so
you have to actually step into a pretty
child's mind place and as a rule of
thumb go very slowly and don't try to
come to doing come to action very
quickly I'm gonna step by step you have
to learn was it here to stand before you
walk and if you walk before you run and
this is very much a developmental so
within that context what are some of the
core capacities that are part of our
development of stage for this to
actually be able to move this
decentralized collective intelligence
forward there are many others and I'll
come to some of those during this series
but I also want to point to Daniel SHM
Acton Berger's work in particular in the
war on sense making series that we've
put out how do we make good choices if
we don't have good sense making
obviously we can't but due to increasing
technological capacity right increasing
population multiplied by increasing
impact per person we're making more and
more consequential choices with worse
and worse sense making to inform those
choices which is kind of running
increasingly fast through the woods
increasingly blind right
and so I think many of the people that
you've had on revell ISM have been in a
deep inquiry around how do we actually
fix our own sense-making and its some of
what has brought us to have
conversations with each other because a
part of how we work with our own sense
making as we recognize the cognitive
complexity of issues that the world
faces is more than a single person can
process a single brain that can't
actually hold that cognitive complexity
so it requires collective intelligence
and collective sense making
but I can't just offload the cognitive
complexity to some Authority because I
can't trust that they're actually doing
good sense making maybe they're doing
good sense making within a very limited
context but then the application of that
outside of the context is different and
maybe there's even distortions within
their context so I have to try and find
other people that are also really
endeavoring to sense make well which
means they have to understand what
causes failures and sense making and
then we have to see can we create
relationships with each other that
remove the distortion basis that is
normally there what can people do right
now within a game theoretic world to
start to create spaces of truthfulness
start to create relationships where one
of the highest values is truthfulness
with other people that are capable of
and want and are committed to that where
people are not only not lying to each
other but they are endeavouring to not
withhold information which is a
tremendous intimacy and tremendous
vulnerability and see if you can create
enough psychological safety with some
people to be able to start exploring
what does it mean to actually share
information honestly so that we can have
that and all kind of make sense together
that's one thing
and there's also something where it's
like if you don't throw trash out the
window of your car because you don't
pollute the environment be careful about
not polluting the information ecology by
rationalizing why your own miss or
disinformation is okay and just start to
think of it that way think of anytime
you're sharing a little lies as as
polluting the information ecology and
being like oh wow I don't want to do
that I would I don't want to be part of
the fucked up information ecology so I
hope that was useful as a bit of framing
I'll release my talk on the IDW tomorrow
and then continue this series probably
over the next three or four weeks rebel
wisdom was set up to make sense of the
world at a deeper level than the
mainstream media it was built for these
times of crisis and change which is why
we want to do what we can to meet the
challenge of the times more films and
also for our rebel wisdom members weekly
sense-making calls with our amazing
interviewees and also we're introducing
the wisdom gym a place to practice some
of the skills that we've talked about on
the channel thanks for watching and see
you soon